Guide to the Associated Alumni Files 1880-1970 (bulk 1916-1948)
Brown University Library
Associated Alumni Files
1880-1970
(bulk 1916-1948)
OF-1S-1
John Hay Library University Archives and Manuscripts Box A Brown University Providence, RI, 02912 Telephone: Manuscripts: 401-863-3723; University Archives: 401-863-2148 Email: Manuscripts: hay@brown.edu; University Archives: archives@brown.edu
17.75 linear feet
Associated Alumni
The Associated Alumni Files includes committee files, meeting minutes, and reports dated from 1880 to 1970, with most dated from 1916 to 1948. It includes materials regarding class reunions, constitutions, commencements, the Brown Club, the Advisory Board, Board of Directors, Executive Committee, Alumni Fund, and general files.
Biographical/Historical Note
The Associated Alumni was incorporated in 1919, when the organization known as the Alumni Association until 1891 and as the Associated Alumni since 1892 reorganized under a new constitution designed to involve the alumni in closer cooperation with the University. The first meeting of an alumni association recorded was in 1823. A later alumni association was formed in response to resolutions by Professor William G. Goddard at a meeting of the alumni on September 6, 1842, with the intent of bringing together annually the graduates of the University to attend literary exercises and share a dinner.
In 1868 President Caswell revived the association by inviting the alumni to a meeting before Commencement to consult on the interests of the University, specifically the founding of scholarships. A committee of the alumni reported in 1869 in favor of a permanent association to meet annually at Commencement and recommended the formation of local associations. Thus the Brown Clubs began, as the local associations were established in New York in 1869, and in Philadelphia and Boston in 1870. “Articles of Organization of the Alumni Association of Brown University” were adopted on June 25, 1872. A resolution passed the next year provided for the annual election of seven persons to constitute an Advisory Board of the Alumni to consult with the government of the University on matters relating to its interests and to submit suitable candidates for consideration in filling vacancies on the Board of Trustees. In 1875 the Corporation and the Alumni agreed on a plan allowing the alumni to vote on nominations for trustees of the University.
At the 1919 annual meeting a new constitution under the name, “Associated Alumni of Brown University, Incorporated” was proposed and accepted. The new constitution provided for the creation of an executive committee, the addition of a faculty member to the advisory board, the creation of a paid office of alumni manager, the establishment of an alumni register, and annual dues of three dollars. A further reorganization of the Associated Alumni in 1973 provided for an executive committee made up of the four elected officers, five appointed local directors, and 62 appointed regional directors. In 1973 the Alumnae Association merged with the Associated Alumni, and in 1979 Phyllis Van Horn Tillinghast ’51 became the first woman president of the Associated Alumni.
Collection information
The papers are arranged into eight series:
Series 1. Bound records (1916-1939): this series includes an alphabetical arrangement of bounded books covering ledgers, office accounts, and subscriptions.
Series 2. Constitution and by-laws (1922-1970): this series includes numerous files regarding the Association's constitution, by-laws, and amendments.
Series 3. Advisory Board (1919-1946): this series includes numerous files, arranged chronollogically, covering Advisory Board meeting minutes, attendance, proceedings, reports, correspondence, resolution, and other programs.
Series 4. Board of Directors (1935-1975): this series includes numerous files, arranged alphabetically, covering the Board of Directors's meeting minutes, correspondence, and elections.
Series 5. Executive Committee (1930-1958): this series includes files, arranged chronologically, that mostly span the Executive Committee's meeting minutes, and correspondence.
Series 6. Brown Alumni Fund (1936-1960): this series includes files of trustee meeting minutes, alumni newsletters, and correspondence between the Brown Fund. It is mostly arranged chronologically.
Series 7. General Files (1884-1954): this series includes numerous files concerning committees, events, and people at Brown University, including the Alumni Fund, the Brown Club, elections, and class reunions. It is arranged alphabetically.
Series 8. Miscellaneous (1880-1982): this series contains files that were later added to the collection, including the Brown Fund Annual Report, Associated Alumni board meeting notes, and career night plans.
There are no restrictions on access, except that the collection can only be seen by prior appointment. Some materials may be stored off-site and cannot be produced on the same day on which they are requested.
Series 1. Bound records
Series 2. Constitution and by-laws
Series 3. Advisory Board
Series 4. Board of Directors
Series 5. Executive Committee
Series 6. Brown Alumni Fund
Series 7. General Files
Series 8. Miscellaneous
- Bound records, 1916-1939; Series 1
  - Alumni fund ledger, 1925-1928 (Box 1, Folder I.2)
    Missing as of February 21, 2020
  - Alumni fund ledger, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder I.3)
  - Alumni office accounts and subscriptions, 1919-1920 (Box 1, Folder I.4)
  - Alumni office accounts and subscriptions, 1921-1925 (Box 1, Folder I.5)
  - Alumni office accounts and subscriptions, 1922-1924 (Box 1, Folder I.6)
  - Register of alumni attending Commencement, 1922-1925 (Box 1, Folder I.7)
  - Register of alumni attending Commencement, 1926-1939 (Box 1, Folder I.8)
- Constitution and by-laws, 1922-1970; Series 2
- Advisory Board, 1919-1946; Series 3
- Board of Directors, 1935-1975; Series 4
- Executive Committee, 1930-1958; Series 5
- Brown Alumni Fund, 1936-1960; Series 6
- General Files, 1884-1954; Series 7
- Miscellaneous, 1880-1982; Series 8